Taiwan is the wealthiest place on Earth
that faces such a credible near-term
threat of getting invaded by a stronger
power. That's because its neighbor, the
People's Republic of China, believes the
island of Taiwan is an integral part of
its territory and that reunification is
not only ideal but necessary. [music]
And PRC leadership has explicitly said
that the achievement of this necessity
might require military force and tasked
its People's Liberation Army with being
prepared to invade the island by 2027.
Taiwan's odds do not look good on paper.
China's PLA is the world's largest
military as measured by active duty
personnel and second largest when
measured on the basis of spending. It
has more combat aircraft than anyone but
the United States, more aircraft
carriers than anyone but the United
States, more amphibious warfare ships
than anyone. Given Russia's failure in
Ukraine, it's hard to argue that China
is not the world's second strongest
military power, and its central guiding
goal is being able to invade and hold
this small but strategically and
politically valuable neighboring island.
But in spite of that, military analysts
believe Taiwan actually has a chance.
Not necessarily a good one, but a real
one nonetheless. And it's all thanks to
its geography. Most notably, Taiwan's an
island. Without a land route like when
Russia invaded Ukraine, the start of an
invasion becomes stunningly predictable.
China would simply have to stage an
[music] amphibious assault. There's just
no way it could achieve a full takeover
through paratroopers or air strikes
alone. This amphibious assault would
initially focus on capturing and then
defending a beach to act as its
logistical entry point to the island was
called a beach head. Effectively, they'd
be trying to replicate D-Day. The
trouble for the PLA is that D-Day is
still to this day the largest amphibious
landing ever conducted with about
150,000 Allied troops attacking and then
defending their beach head in Normandy.
But China's effort would be harder. Back
in 1944, the Allies had the element of
surprise. With a lack of electronic
surveillance that allowed for successful
deception efforts, German forces did not
know with confidence that the boats were
coming for Normandy until troops saw
them with their own eyes. While German
Central Command had some understanding
that an invasion effort was coming, the
lack of certainty on where meant they
were unable to reinforce Normandy ahead
of the landing, allowing the Allies to
go against relatively weak German
defenses in the initial phase of
invasion. The PLA doesn't have that
luxury. Analysts believe an invasion
force would need to number around 4 to
500,000
personnel to have a realistic shot of
toppling the ROC. And assembling and
staging these troops and their equipment
on the mainland would be a monthslong
process, almost impossible to hide. But
the predictability goes further. The
Taiwan Strait [music] is far rougher
than the English Channel on average. and
amphibious landings rely on near-perfect
sea conditions to prevent landing craft
from getting swamped and also quite
literally to stop troops from getting
seasick, inhibiting their effectiveness
when storming the beach. Clear skies are
also necessary in maximizing the chances
of success to allow air assets to
operate without restraint. And these
sorts of sea and air conditions should
ideally last for days or weeks to allow
[music] for a steady stream of
reinforcements to arrive uninhibited.
Taiwan's annual weather patterns are
quite structured. [music] In winter, the
island is hit by a northeast monsoon
that blows strong winds towards [music]
it, generating rough sea conditions in
the straight for months on end that
inhibit an amphibious landing. This
subsides in spring and wave heights
lower into summer. But that's when
typhoon season starts. Typhoon tracks
can only be accurately forecasted 3 to 5
[music] days out, meaning the PLA can
never have certainty about the 2 or 3
week weather window needed for the best
shot of a successful invasion during
summer. That leaves two key weather
windows, April and October. Taiwan knows
this. [music] If they see a month-long
buildup, it's likeliest to translate
into an invasion during one of these two
months, allowing their military to
mobilize in step. And even once an
invasion started, the 100 m or 160 km of
separation between the island and China
would give Taiwan about a 10-hour head
start. Of course, much of what would
happen in those hours is a massive air
campaign to strike and destroy as many
of the PLA ships as possible. But as
that went on, ground forces would move
to defend potential landing sites, and
still then there's plenty of
predictability.
You see, the majority of Taiwan's
coastline is just not suited for an
amphibious assault. Most of the East
Coast features massive cliffs, making
movement inland near impossible. Much of
the West Coast is made up of muddy
wetlands that would quickly trap landing
vehicles. Substantial other portions
have been developed into aquaculture
farms growing oysters, shrimp or fish.
Meaning the coastal landscape is dotted
with hundreds of small pools
concentrating invading vehicles onto
limited and easily defensible roads.
Among the beaches, they need the slope
of the ground beneath the water to be
steep enough to allow for landing craft
to get close to shore. But then for the
beach to have a shallow slope to allow
vehicles to drive up easily, and it's
got to be wide enough to give space for
the sizable force. Taken together, there
are very few Goldilocks Normandy style
beaches that allow for the successful
landing and onward push of hundreds of
thousands of troops. Analysts believe
they have the number down to just 14.
And though it's debated exactly how
constrained the PLA is with their
options given advances in technology,
either way, Taiwan's natural defenses
allow its military to concentrate its
resources into limited areas. But
between what's left, perhaps the most
attractive landing site is here, Linka
and Bali North beaches. Beyond their
physical compatibility, they feature
proximity to key strategic assets that
China [music] would benefit from
capturing quickly. In between the two
beaches is the port of Taipei. While
China is known to be developing floating
barges that can act as peers to allow
for large non-mphibious vessels to
unload personnel and cargo, capturing a
permanent port facility would likely
allow for more capacity with less
vulnerability to attack. Similarly,
slightly further on, there's Talion
International Airport, the country's
largest, which could act as an on island
air base for the PLA as it works towards
a complete capture. But perhaps the
biggest advantage of this landing site
is its proximity to the Tamui River,
allowing small, fast boats a quick route
into central Taipei. From the river's
banks, it's just a mile to the
presidential palace, whose capture would
mark the biggest symbolic defeat for
Taiwan. It's largely for this reason, in
fact, that French Marines landed nearby
on the opposite bank of the mouth of the
river during the Sino French War in
1884. Their invasion ultimately failed,
though, for largely the same reason why
China would struggle. It's just too easy
to predict and therefore defend against.
Therefore, these beaches are some of the
most frequent hosts of Taiwan's annual
military drills. Over the years, they've
ran simulations of essentially every
phase of an invasion. In 2022, mimicking
a buildup phase, reserveists worked to
rapidly construct a trench facility from
which soldiers could fire onto the beach
stocked with supplies to last up to 30
days. The next year, with the president
watching on, the military conducted a
full amphibious landing drill with one
side standing in as the PLA, while the
other worked to stop them from their
hardened positions. Over the next few
years, there were at least four separate
exercises related to countering an
offensive via the Tempsu River. The
Taiwanese side's tactic was to place
floating gasoline barrels rigged with C4
explosives to be set off as Chinese
vessels attempted to make their way
through. But they also simulated
exploding Guandu Bridge in order to
physically block vessels from advancing
further down the river and into Taipei.
But what this strategically critical
area lacks is infrastructure. You can
find a 17th century fort built by the
Spanish Empire along the river's mouth
and cold war era pill boxes dotting the
beach, but no permanent modern
fortifications. This is the likeliest
starting point of one of the likeliest
theoretical conflicts on Earth. And yet,
it looks like any other beach. That's
because Taiwan just doesn't believe in
permanent coastal defense
infrastructure, thinking its
vulnerability would mean it would almost
certainly get destroyed through air
strikes before the first boats even
arrived. Rather, Taiwan builds its
greatest military infrastructure in its
most defensible positions. You see,
while preventing China from successfully
establishing a beach head would be the
most effective way for Taiwan to
prevail. And while amphibious landings
are an incredibly tricky military
maneuver, they give a massive advantage
to the defending side, it's important
that the nation's survival does [music]
not hinge on it. There's just a
tremendous power imbalance between the
two militaries. If China breaks through,
Taiwan's best hope is that friendly
countries, Japan, South Korea, the
Philippines, Australia, and most
critically the US join the fight. But
reinforcements would take time to
arrive. So, the military has invested in
asssuring it can maintain a foothold on
the island for as long as possible.
That's why deep beneath this mountain
just north of central Taipei is the Hen
Shawn Command Center. Very little is
known about this facility beyond the
fact that it exists. It's supposedly
connected to the Ministry of National
Defense headquarters by tunnel. There
are apparently other entrances around
the mountain. It's intended to house the
president as they lead the war effort.
It can survive nuclear blasts and EMPs,
but the details pretty much end there.
This is one of the only photos ever
released from the inside depicting
former President Saiing Wen in the
facility as she received a briefing.
Slightly more is known about the
country's other most defensible
facility, Jaan Air Force Base. Shaon is
located on Taiwan's far less populated
east coast in the outskirts of the city
of Haleian. It's about as far from China
as one can get on the island, meaning
it'd be just about the least accessible
location to a force invading from the
west thanks to the enormous peaks
stretching close to 13,000 ft or 4,000 m
standing [music] in the way. But that's
not what makes this site so resilient.
This is these are the entrances to an
underground hanger complex believed to
be capable of storing 200 fighter jets.
That's about twothirds of the country's
entire inventory and more than that of
all but a dozen or so entire air forces
worldwide. These are some of the only
photos ever released from inside it
showing an F-16 being loaded with an
anti-ship missile. But of course, this
air base has a vulnerability. The
fighter jets might be safe, but they
can't do much without a working runway.
When this facility was originally built,
missiles were not accurate enough to
make precision strikes on runways from
the distances that they'd likely be
fired from. But that's no longer the
case. It's for this reason that the
military recently expanded this and
other airbases runways to a uniquely
wide 200 f feet or 60 m. Fighter jets
only need a third of that width to
reliably take off and land. So even if a
missile does successfully strike,
there's a greater chance that there'd
still be a lane to keep operating with.
Meanwhile, Taiwanese troops constantly
drill their rapid runway repair
capabilities and can reportedly patch an
impact crater in just 2 and 1/2 hours.
But just like with coastal defenses,
Taiwan's airbase strategy focuses on
resilience through adaptability. That's
why across the country, there are
sections of regular highways like this.
This stretch has been built wider and
with stronger asphalt than most in order
to serve as a temporary air base in
wartime. There are no overhead
obstacles, and the barriers in the
center are easily removable, so
adaptation can happen in about 24 to 48
hours.
Now, Taiwan's defense doctrine is often
described as the porcupine strategy.
They seek to make it so costly for China
to invade [music] that they just decide
not to. This became the formal doctrine
in 2017 when it became clear that Taiwan
no longer had any realistic shot of
matching China's military power headon.
The PLA had just amassed too many
soldiers, fighter jets, missiles,
drones. They'd amassed too much
capability. So, rather Taiwan shifted to
an asymmetric strategy. They'd pursue
less capable but less expensive
platforms to make their dollar stretch
further and therefore [music] acquire
more. Particularly, they'd search for
ways to destroy costly Chinese [music]
equipment for a fraction of the cost.
For example, prior to this focus,
Taiwan's navy did buy four highly
capable former US Navy destroyers for
$732 million. But these ships would
inevitably and quickly become [music]
prime targets for China's fighter jets
and missiles. So Taiwan equipped 42 far
smaller [music] vessels with four
missiles each so their offensive
capability would be distributed more
widely. These smaller missile boats are
easier for China to attack and destroy,
but the number of them would make it
costly and difficult for the PLA to
destroy them before the bulk of their
offensive capabilities are used.
Similarly, the ROC Navy has recently
invested heavily in its mine lane
capabilities as mines are an inexpensive
but relatively effective defensive
weapon. But the core of the porcupine
doctrine has been Taiwan's [music]
missile buildout. Following the imminent
arrival of a massive order of US-made
Harpoon [music] missiles, the military
will have over 1,400, meaning Taiwan
will have the highest concentration of
anti-hship missiles in the world. These,
of course, would be critical to inflict
as much damage as possible on the PLA
landing force before it [music] arrives,
seeking to push numbers below the
threshold needed to take the island. But
Taiwan's defense strategy has its
critics. Military analysts argue that
the porcupine strategy is right, but
that they don't embrace it enough. For
example, the ROC had a prototype for an
even smaller fast-moving catamaran
missile boat operated by a crew of just
three. They were slated to order 60 of
these, pushing the distribution of its
missiles to a further extreme until the
entire program got indefinitely delayed.
Rather, they spent $8 billion on 66 new
F-16 fighter jets and $1.28 to $8
billion for 108 new ABS tanks. Both
highly capable pieces of equipment, but
ones that are sure to become Chinese
missile magnets. But then Ukraine
happened. What was once considered the
world's second most powerful military
invaded a comparatively tiny neighbor
and failed. Ukraine essentially put
Taiwan's porcupine strategy into
practice [music] and succeeded. So, the
ROC has learned endlessly from this
conflict. But perhaps the most notable
piece is the newfound relevance of
consumergrade [music] drones. Just as
they did in Ukraine, these could play a
huge role in Taiwan, even in that first
critical phase of pushing back the
amphibious invasion. But perhaps the one
geographic disadvantage of Taiwan is
that once again, it's an island. From
day one of an invasion, and very
possibly before, external supply lines
would essentially cease to exist. It's
in part for that reason that they've
invested heavily over the past 2 years
in building up a domestic drone
manufacturing industry. And it's
maximizing the definition of domestic,
creating a $ 1.5 billion program to
subsidize manufacturers in exchange for
an assurance that no component is
sourced from mainland China. Something
easier said than done in an industry 80%
concentrated there. Of course, the other
side of Taiwan's porcupine strategy, one
centered on maximizing destruction to
dissuade invasion, is that if Xiinping
follows through on his threats, if China
does seek to capture its neighbor,
[music] it would be a horrifically,
inconceivably bloody war. Taiwan has
every right to defend itself if attacked
by the PLA, but in doing so, it would
unleash a scale and sort of violence
unseen this century. The hope is that
the certainty of this outcome would
prevent it from unfolding, but the fear
is that reason regularly fails and that
the People's Republic of China could
make an era defining decision to attack
the Republic of China.
Preparing for the future is not only a
theme of this video, it's the guiding
characteristic defining my relationship
with the sponsor of today's video,
Chime. Chime is America's number one
choice for banking for good reason. It
provides an awesome, dependable, and
approachable service. Open up a Chime
account and you'll feel like the service
is actually working for you. There are
no monthly fees, no overdraft fees, and
if you want to start seeing your savings
[music] grow, Chime offers a 3.75%
annual percentage yield. That's 9 times
the national average. This makes Chime a
great service to start making some
financial headway with less headaches
and paperwork because it can all be done
through the app. And another awesome
feature is that when money does get a
little tight, Chime offers an early
payday feature where should you need
access to money from your upcoming
direct deposit paycheck, you can access
up to $500 before the check actually
hits, which can be huge when you're in a
pinch. And following this same people
first approach, Chime now offers the
Chime card, a secured Visa credit card
that earns 5% [music] cash back with no
annual fees, allowing you to spend more
effectively while also building your
credit score. The card can even be set
to safer credit building, which will
have your account automatically pay off
the card on time with funds saved in
your account to ensure no missed due
dates and subsequent credit score slips.
Navigating the world of money management
is just a pain and something I
personally don't want to spend all my
free time trying to understand. So, it
makes me really happy that a service
like Chime exists and that they're
interested in partnering with us as a
channel. Give Chime a go by following
the link in this video's description,
chime.com/wendover,
or the QR code on screen. It only takes
two minutes, and if you do it now, you
can get a bonus of up to $350
exclusively through my link.